<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the ministers of Christ from the slander cast on them that they are house-creepers, because they sometimes preach in private houses : also proving by the Scripture who are house-creepers, and the evil they do where their corrupt doctrine is received / held forth in two sermons on 2 Tim. 3. 6., by W.E.</title>
            <author>W. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E44</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15609401</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15609401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1590:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the ministers of Christ from the slander cast on them that they are house-creepers, because they sometimes preach in private houses : also proving by the Scripture who are house-creepers, and the evil they do where their corrupt doctrine is received / held forth in two sermons on 2 Tim. 3. 6., by W.E.</title>
                  <author>W. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Pike ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 43 misprinted 42.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, III, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England.</term>
               <term>House churches --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE Miniſters OF CHRIST FROM That Slander caſt on them, that they Are HOUSE-CREEPERS, becauſe they ſometimes Preach in private Houſes.</p>
            <p>ALSO Proving by the Scripture who are <hi>Houſe-Creepers,</hi> and the evil they do where their corrupt Doctrine is Received.</p>
            <p>Held forth in two SERMONS on 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 PET. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> But there were falſe prophets among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe teachers among you, which ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VER 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> And many ſhall follow their pernicious ways, by whom the Way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Pike</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſet</hi> Book-binder and Book-ſeller. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104103:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THESE are to aſſure Thee, that the Author of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Diſcourſe, never intended it for the Preſs, being ſenſible of his own weakneſs. But by Providence it is thus brought about: He being deſired by ſome friends to open this Scripture in <hi>2 Tim. 3.6.</hi> This Text being made uſe of by ſome to diſcourage Perſons from attending the Ordinances of God in private places; Although through the great Mercy of God, and the favour of the King, they cannot properly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led private Places, ſince the Places are appointed by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and it is free for any to come unto them; They make uſe of this Scripture to ſeare the weak from coming thither, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting unto them, that thoſe who preach in ſuch places are the Perſons that the Apoſtle here calls <hi>Creepers into Houſes,</hi> and the ſame that he calls <hi>ver. 13. wicked men and deceivers:</hi> And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Scripture they make uſe of as the Great Engine to batter down all ſuch Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>This enſuing Diſcourſe is to ſhew, who were thoſe tht the Apoſtle here calls <hi>Houſe-creepers;</hi> And that they have not this denomination given them on this account, becauſe they did preach in Houſes, for it was the frequent Practices of this and the reſt of the Apoſtles, yea, of Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>But it was becauſe theſe here ſpoken of did chuſe private Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the end that they might ſteal the hearts of the ſimple from the truth, and their wiles might not be diſcerned, yea, thoſe who under the pretence of truth; with fair words beguile the hearts of the ſimple, are the ſame with thoſe the Apoſtle here calls <hi>Houſe-creepers,</hi> although they appear in publick Places.</p>
            <p>This being a ſubject ſeldom reated of, ſome having taken the Notes of the Diſcourſe, were very earneſt to ſend it to the Preſſe, which the Author was unwilling ſhould be done: But this Argument prevailed with him to give his Conſent; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that ſome Perſon whom the Lord hath endowed with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Gifts and Learning, might from hence be provoked to put forth his Abilities, for the further clearing up this Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lawfulneſs of Aſſembling together to wait on God in his Ordinances, in ſuch Places, which ſome by way of ſcorn call
<pb facs="tcp:104103:3"/>private Places; And that thoſe Miniſters who do endeavour faithfully to perform their duty in ſuch Places, are not of thoſe who are here condemned by the Apoſtle, but ſuch as did follow the Example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; that ſo thoſe that are weak might not be affrighted by ſuch Bug-bears: If any ſhall receive benefit by theſe weak Endeavours, Give the glory to the Lord, to whom alone it is due, that hath enabled ſo weak a Creature to ſpeak a word for the truth, that is ſo much deſpiſed by many; the Lord make it a good word to the Souls of his People. This is the earneſt deſire and hearty Prayer of Him who wiſheth Peace and Proſperity to all the Churches of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104103:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 TIM. 3.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For of this Sort are they which creep into Houſes, and lead Captive ſilly Women with divers luſts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle in the Beginning of the Chapter, by the Spirit of Prophecy doth foretel, That the laſt days ſhall be peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and full of danger; and then what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it, as you may ſee 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>For men ſhall be Lovers of their own ſelves, Covetous, Boaſters, &amp;c.</hi> So that there are in it theſe two things Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in the laſt dayes there ſhall be peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the reaſon of ſuch perillous times is, becauſe men abound in ſin and wickedneſs; Whence obſerve by the way,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That abundance of iniquity makes Perillous Times.</hi> This is very clear in the Scriptures. You may ſee, that when Holineſs doth increaſe, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons make it their buſineſs to walk according to Gods Word, at ſuch times there is happineſs and great Bleſſings vouchſafed unto a people. So on the other Hand, when people Apoſtatize and fall from God, then uſually ſuch times are full of danger. It was a time full of danger with <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104103:4"/>when ſin and wickedneſs abounded among them, and they departed from God, and apoſtatized from the purity of his worſhip <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.14.15. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. v 8.12. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. v. 1.2. <hi>ch.</hi> 6. v. 1.2.3.4.5.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.4. When people turn aſide from God and ſet up their own luſts, they ſhall have ſorrow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And again, when people make it their buſineſs to walk with God, all things proſper with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.3.4.5.10.11.12. The like you have in the dayes of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. but when men forſake the Commandments of the Lord, and walk contrary to him, God hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy with ſuch a land. It is the abundance of iniquity that makes times perillous <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you two reaſons of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Times are uſually full of danger when ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity abounds, becauſe God uſually appears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe when iniquity abounds, people allow themſelves to walk after their own luſts, they are ready to break out into any wickedneſs: there is nothing within them to reſtrain them, but they are ready to do whatſoever their baſe hearts prompt them to, though it be never ſo groſſely prejudicious to mens eſtates, lives, or liberties. I might much enlarge here: But <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſpeak no further to this.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the dependence of the text, on the foregoing words. Now ſaith the text, <hi>For of this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104103:4"/>ſort are they that creep into houſes.</hi> Of what ſort? of the ſort here mentioned, ſuch has had a form of godlineſs, but denyed the power thereof.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of ſuch that were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that had no knowledge of God, and made profeſſion of religion, but of ſuch as profeſſed God, and that they were the friends of God. For, ſaith the text <hi>(having a form of godlineſs)</hi> they had a form of godlineſs, but they denyed the power thereof: They pretended much for Chriſt and the waies of Chriſt, but denyed that which was the main, <hi>viz.</hi> a full ſubmiſſion of themſelves to Chriſt, to walk according to the rules of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now every particular of this might cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be proved concerning the Antichriſtian power, the myſtery of iniquity, and thoſe that are plunged into it. The text ſaith, they have a form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; and have not theſe? Do not they pretend much for Chriſt? when none do oppoſe him more. Are not they lovers of pleaſures, more then lovers of God? May it not be clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that notwithſtanding their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for Chriſt, they ſtand in open oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt him in all his Offices? As firſt for his prophetical office, they are ſo far from hearkning to the voice of Chriſt, that they ſet up their own inventions in the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, preferring them before his inſtitutions.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104103:5"/>They obey not Chriſt as the great Prophet ſo that if thoſe, on whom they urge their inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould demand, <hi>What Word of God have you for theſe things?</hi> They would return nothing but ſcoffs,</p>
            <p>Again, as for Chriſts Prieſtly Office, what a diſhonour is it to Chriſt, that they make their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloody ſacrifice of the Altar to be a Propitiation for the ſins of men?</p>
            <p>And as for Chriſts Kingly Office, they have no regard to the Authority of Chriſt, nor to the Rule that he hath appointed for the Government of the Church, nor have they any reſpect to the Spirit of God, but make a mock of him, though it be ſo clear in the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 14 They are ſo far from walking according to the Word of God, that they walk contrary to it: ſo far from ſubduing their ſinful pollutions, that they endeavor by all means to cheriſh them, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Works of Prayer, Charity, Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as meritorious, they pretend much honour to the Croſs of Chriſt, but on every trivial oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion make nothing to ſwear by his blood and wounds: they pretend much to Prayer, Reading with hands and eyes lifted up; yet how far are they from that ſpiritual zeal and fervour of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that is neceſſarily requiſite in Prayer. <hi>Having a Forme of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104103:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now, <hi>of this ſort are they that creep into Houſes, leading Captive filly Women,</hi> &amp;c. under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being for God, they deceive people, and draw them into pernicious errours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leading Captive ſilly Women.</hi> They uſually aſſault ſuch, becauſe by reaſon of the weakneſs of their ſex and underſtanding, they are not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern their wiles and ſubtilties. For obſerve, that it is not ſpoken generally of Women. But</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Silly Women.</hi> Such as are ignorant of the Truth of God, that content themſelves with an outward profeſſion, not endeavouring to be firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded and eſtabliſhed in the things of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as were laden with fin, led away with divers luſts, that though they lived under a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion, and contented themſelves, becauſe they apprehended they had ſome deſires, or at leaſt ſome kinde of affection to the truth, yet they were under the power of their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now ſuch that are wilfully captivated to their luſts, it is no wonder, if God ſuffer them in his juſt Judgment to be enſnared by thoſe that lie in wait to deceive them.</p>
            <p>So that the Apoſtle means by <hi>ſilly women</hi> all ſuch, as either by reaſon of the weakneſs of their underſtanding, being not able to diſcern the wiles and craftineſs of deceivers, or ſuch as being under the power and dominion of ſome luſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104103:6"/>God in his juſt judgment ſuffers to be enſnared by them. Thus you have the ſenſe of the words. In the words you have obſervable theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The perſons here ſpoken of, called by the Apoſtle, creepers into houſes. <hi>viz.</hi> falſe teachers.</p>
            <p>The deſcription of them, <hi>Of this ſort are they.</hi> He ſheweth their evil qualities in the precedent verſes, <hi>They are lovers of themſelves, covetous, beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, proud, curſed ſpeakers, without natural affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, deſpiſers of them that are good. Traitours, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God: Having a forme of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof.</hi> Of this ſort are they, ſaith he, as much as to ſay, this is a plain and full deſcription of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſheweth what fad works theſe make where they creep into houſes, <hi>they lead cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The perſons that they prevaile on, <hi>Silly women,</hi> which is not to be underſtood only of that ſex, but perſons that are ſimple, void of underſtanding as to ſpiritual things whether men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe perſons that are thus led captive are more fully deſcribed by that corrupt ſtate they are in, <hi>viz.</hi> They are ſuch as are laden with ſin, ſuch as are under the power and dominion of ſome baſe luſt or luſts: Theſe are they who are made a prey of by them. Now here obſerve.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104103:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That men are not accounted theſe houſe creepers in the Scripture account, or in the account of the Apoſtle, becauſe they do preach in houſes or ſecret places: but when they get into ſuch places, and there under the pretence of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs make it their buſineſs ſecretly to draw ſuch as are weak from the truth to error; and thoſe who chuſe ſuch places to carry on their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, may juſtly be called creepers: yea, all that in their teaching carry on ſuch a deſign under the pretence of holyneſs, although they preach in the moſt publick places, and in the greateſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies; yet in the Apoſtles ſence here they are creepers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That ſuch perſons uſually effect their deſign on ſuch as are either weak and ignorant, not able to diſcern their corrupt and unſound doctrine; or ſuch as are under the power of ſome baſe luſt or luſts, be they men or women, (for it may be underſtood of both ſexes) ſuch being by the juſt judgment of God left to themſelves, and ſo they eaſily prevaile on them.</p>
            <p>For the proof of the firſt Doctrine, <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you ſeveral Scriptures, by which this ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appeares Conſider that place <hi>John</hi> 10.1. <hi>He that climbeth in ſome other way, he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth not by the door is a thief and a robber.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104103:7"/>Now the <hi>Door</hi> is Chriſt by which Men enter, when they are ſent of Chriſt, (as certainly Chriſt ſendeth none but ſuch as hear his voice, none are his ſheep but ſuch as hear his voice) thoſe then that come in, &amp; not by Chriſt, may well be termed Creepers or Climbers up another way, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.2. We ſhall finde there, that the Apoſtle commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the Goſpel privately to them which were of Reputation; and it was by reaſon of the falſe brethren that crept in amongſt them. So that thoſe Perſons are called Creepers, that under the pretence of Holineſs draw people from the truth, of whom alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Jude v.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding hereof I ſhall ſhew you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in the Apoſtles judgement none were accounted Houſe-creepers, becauſe they did preach in private places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That theſe are to be ſo accounted, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of Holineſs do ſeek to draw people from the truth; and thoſe that do ſo, though never ſo publick, yet come under this Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in the Apoſtles Judgment none were accounted Houſe-creepers, becauſe they did preach in private places; <hi>I</hi> call it private, in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe places that were appointed for the publick Worſhip and Ordinances of God, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104103:7"/>the <hi>Jews</hi> there was the Temple and the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues. Now you ſhall find, that it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, not only in the Temple and Synagogue, but in divers other places to preach the Word. It was juſtified by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. he preached on a Mountain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.2. in a ſhip; and at another time he preached by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſide, and by Jacobs-w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll to the <hi>Samaritane</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; <hi>John</hi> 4. and afterwards to the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> v. 40.41, 42. And this was not only the practice of Chriſt, but of the Apoſtles afterwards, <hi>John</hi> 20.19.26. ſo that at both theſe times they were met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a houſe. So <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12.13, 14. where it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo, that they met together about the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God; for it is ſaid, <hi>they continued with one accord in prayer and ſupplication.</hi> And ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>Peter</hi> preached at <hi>Cornelius</hi>'s houſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13, <hi>Paul</hi> preached at the Rivers ſide, where God opened the heart of <hi>Lydia.</hi> And again at <hi>Athens,</hi> on the midſt of <hi>Mars-hill. Acts</hi> 17.17.22. So you ſee, that it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to preach in ſeveral places, whereſoever Providence caſt them. Hence we may ſafely conclude, That which was the Practice of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles afterwards, cannot be rationally ſuppoſed to be condemned by this expreſſion of the Apoſtle, nor was it the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles intent that perſons ſhould fall under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of <hi>houſe-creepers,</hi> becauſe they taught in private places, ſince it was uſe both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Nay, it is very remarkable and worthy of our obſervation, that the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> as cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as they were, did not (as we read) lay this as a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104103:8"/>ſlaunder on Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for teaching in ſuch places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thoſe indeed are the perſons, whom the Apoſtle means, who putting on an outward ſhow and forme of holyneſs, under that deceive, and lead from the truth. Now this will evidently appear, if you view the words that we read unto you, in which the Apoſtle doth diſcover them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they were ſuch, that had a forme of godlineſs, <hi>Having a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof. For of this ſort, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They were ſuch that under the forme did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by drawing from the truth. So that when men do purpoſely and out of choice take ſuch places, wherein they may carry on their pernicious deſigns, and lead perſons from the truth, theſe in the Scripture ſence, and the Apoſtles judgment are rightly termed houſe-creepers, as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 3.20. <hi>For every one that doth evil hateth the light, neither cometh he to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved.</hi> Such then may be ſaid to be creepers, when they get to ſecret places, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to avoid the light, that their deeds of darkneſs may not be diſcovered. It is beyond all doubt that the Apoſtle meaneth not of ſuch, that were forced and conſtrained to take ſuch places: but doubtleſs the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of thoſe falſe teachers, that had diffuſed their errours, and ſpread themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad amongſt the Churches of God, thinking
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104103:8"/>privately to undermine them: there were ſome of them in <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſome in <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſome in <hi>Philippi,</hi> and <hi>Coloſs</hi> alſo, and at ſeveral other places: and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaketh of it to thoſe to whom he wrote. Such were ready to ſay after this manner: What, will ye not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Commandments of God? Hath not the Lord expreſly Commanded Circumciſion, and the forbearance of ſuch and ſuch meates? Is not this the will of God? and ſo by ſuch fair words, many were ſeduced and drawn away, not being able to diſcover the bottom of their deſigns. You may ſee, how notably the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to the <hi>Coloſſians, Col.</hi> 2.16.17, 18. theſe men pretended much to holyneſs and humility, that they yeilded obedience to God, and had his law amongſt them; but ſee what the Apoſtle ſaith, v. 20. <hi>If then ye be dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world, if ye are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the death of Chriſt, what have you to do with theſe things?</hi> You may ſee, how the Apoſtle takes them off from theſe arguments, they reaſoned thus. This the Law commandeth, therefore we ought to do it: Admit it did ſo, ſaith the Apoſtle, but now by the Death of Chriſt ye are free from theſe things; you are not commanded to forbear ſuch and ſuch meats, but of every creature you may receive: the abſtinence from meates was typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and figurative, but now you are taken of from theſe things: So that the argument hath a double force. If they plead the Law, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ye are dead unto the law.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104103:9"/>
            <p>If they plead the practice of ſome that are wiſe men, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Yea are dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world,</hi> and then ſurely the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men cannot bind you. You are freed from the Doctrines of men, (i.e.) ſuch Doctrines that are not grounded upon the Word of God. So that there may be fair pretences and ſpecious ſhews of holyneſs, when indeed there is no ſuch thing. Now then it appears, that ſince this is not ſpoken of thoſe, that do on ſome occaſion or other preach in private places (for indeed it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles) it muſt be ſpoken of thoſe that do out of voluntary choiſe take ſuch places for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of their wicked deſigns, to entrap ſuch that cannot diſcern their wiles. As for inſtance, when they urge ſuch words as theſe, What will you not be ruled by the Church? will ye not be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Church? this availeth much with ſuch, not conſidering, that the Church is ruled by Gods Word, and what is not according to this Word there is no truth in it; that whatſoever is not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Word, and commanded by God, is will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip; that every plant that God hath not planted, ſhall be plucked up; that things, though done with never ſo much zeale, yet is not warranted by Gods Word, are unacceptable to God; as you may ſee <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. The <hi>Jews</hi> bad obſerved a Faſt in their 70 years captivity; and now upon their return they ſent <hi>Sharezer</hi> and <hi>Regemmelech</hi> to the houſe of God, to know whether they ſhould continue it, yea or no. But ſee what followeth v 5.6, 7. <hi>when ye faſted and mourned in the fifth and ſeventh month, even thoſe</hi> 70
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104103:9"/>
               <hi>years, did ye at all faſt to me, even to me &amp;c.</hi> It was ſuch a ſervice that God had not appointed them, and they going to preſs it on people, God owned it not.</p>
            <p>So that thoſe that under a pretence of holyneſs do endeavour to draw ſouls from the truth, they are thoſe that are the houſe creepers: yea, though they preach in never ſo publick places. For what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there between a Mountebanck that mounteth on a ſtage, and by ſome tricks of Legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main deceiveth the people, and one that doth it in a private place, for it is deceit in both: nay, it is greater impudence in him that doth it publickly, then in him that doth it privately. So is it here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall illuſtrate it by another ſimilitude. As when one cometh into another mans houſe with a vizard, he is judged by the man of the houſe to be ſuch a perſon; but when he diſcovers himſelf, he is found to be another man, then he was thought to be; ſuch a man may be counted a houſe-creeper, though he comes in openly. So it is here, if perſons under the pretence and vizard of holyneſs, do endeavour to deceive the ſimple, they may come under this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of houſe-creepers.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſhew you by ſeveral reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it cannot be underſtood of thoſe that take ſuch places out of neceſſity and conſtraint.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it muſt be meant of ſuch, that under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of holyneſs do endeavour to draw people from the truth; yea, though it be in never ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it cannot be underſtood of thoſe that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104103:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>take ſuch places out of neceſſity and conſtraint.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is not of choice by them, but neceſſity that cauſeth it to be ſo, therefore they ought not to be charged with evil on this account. Could any one rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally accuſe Chriſt, that he preached ſecretly and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, when he withdrew out of <hi>Judea,</hi> and taught <hi>Galilee,</hi> when the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſought his life? Was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to be charged with evil for preaching in a houſe <hi>Acts</hi> 18.6.? when he had before openly reaſoned in the Synagogues with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and they raiſed mutinies &amp; clamours againſt him, and drove him from them. Could the Apoſtles juſtly be blamed, when they met together in private places, and in the night time? And ſo the Church is former times when they were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted violently by the Heathens, and durſt not appear openly. Nay, this truth is ſo evident, that it is granted themſelves, they do even by the Papiſts affirm that in times of perſecution it is meet and neceſſary for the people of God to meet together in private places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OB.</hi> But ſome might ſay, Yes indeed, for Chriſt and his Apoſtles and the people of God in ſuch caſes to meet together, this is graunted, but what's this to <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> and <hi>Hereticks;</hi> theſe may not do ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANS.</hi> But I tell you, it is not mens accuſations that prove it to be ſo, perſons ſhould conſider thus much, that before men can be juſtly charged as <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> &amp; <hi>Heretical,</hi> it ought to be made, by clear and ſolid argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But this we know that in all Countreys they that have the greateſt power condemn all others. If you go to <hi>Rome,</hi> they will tell you that their ſuperſtition is the worſhip of God. So if you go to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> they will tell you that their <hi>Turciſme</hi> and <hi>Mahometiſme</hi> is the right worſhip of God. But perſons ought not to be charged with Hereſy, till they are convinced by ſtrength
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104103:10"/>of argument out of Gods Word. It was a Doctour of the Law that telleth us concerning Chriſt, doth our Law judge any man, before it hath heard him? Nay, you ſhall ſee, it was acknowledged by the very heathens <hi>Acts</hi> 25.5.16. we ſhould not then that bear the name of Chriſtians, be more unreaſonable then the heathens; but take heed of paſſing ſuch peremptory ſentences, before the matter be proved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe what they do they do in ſimplicity and ſincerity of heart, without any deſigns of their own 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. where the Apoſtle ſpeaking of himſelf and of the reſt of the faith full, proveth that they were not of thoſe deceivers, v. 2. <hi>We</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have renounced the hidden things of darkneſs, we have not walked in craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, we have not handled the word of God deceitfully,</hi> and what is that? It may be this, that when men ſee, it is beſt for their intereſt, then they can plead for the Word but when it is a diſadvantage to them in the world, then they can make uſe of the Word to decry theſe things that formerly they cried up, theſe are thoſe whom the Apoſtle means that handled the Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully; but we were not of theſe, and why? becauſe we handl'd the word by manifeſtation of the truth, the conſciences of our hearers can acquit us, that we have endeavour'd to ſet before them the mind &amp; will of God.</p>
            <p>It cannot be underſtood that theſe ſhould be the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here mentioned, becauſe then the Apoſtle would condemn himſelf and the practice of all the reſt of his fellow Apoſtles; nay of the Lord his Maſter. Now it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be rationally imagined, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> who was infallibly guided by the bleſſed Spirit of God, ſhould thus miſcarry, and give occaſion to his adverſaries to triumph, they would have ſaid;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104103:11"/>Look here, he condemneth himſelf, he is one of thoſe that preach in Houſes. But then</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be meant of ſuch, that under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Holineſs, do endeavor to draw perſons from the truth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be underſtood of theſe, becauſe theſe are not the perſons that they ſeem to be, for they come under the Guiſe of Holineſs, pretending much good to the ſouls of men, but yet aim chiefly at ſome deſignes of their own; theſe are the perſons the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, and therefore he giveth them this name of Houſe-creepers; ſo that thoſe who get into the Church of God, (be it either in private or publick places) under a pretence of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when indeed it is not ſo, but there is ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign in their entrance, they are ſuch that do creep in, but they do not enter; for they are not ſuch as they were ſuppoſed to be. And therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>There are certain men crept in unawares;</hi> the Church was not aware of them, they deceive them by their wiles, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore properly ſuch are the Houſe creepers, much like unto the Thief that comes into a Mans Houſe, and is diſguiſed; when he is in he ſpoils and robs: he may be ſaid to creep in, becauſe though he was let in, yet he was not let in as ſuch an one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they purpoſely chooſe ſuch places, and out of a deſign they love ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crecy, that they might not be diſcovered, but carry on their deſignes the more undiſcernably. It is one thing for a mon to take ſecret places out of neceſſity, and another thing to chuſe ſuch places purpoſely. Now the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104103:11"/>Scripture telleth us, <hi>that he that is evil hateth the Light.</hi> Hence it is that the Apoſtle calleth ſuch creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in another place, deceitfull workers, for they are equivalent 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14. <hi>They are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers.</hi> But if they are ſo, how are they then admitted into the Church? oh, ſaith he, <hi>(trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt)</hi> they make pretences of holyneſs, and ſhroud their wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh nature in a Lambs-skin. And they are ſuch too, whoſe intent is the ſame, though it be never ſo openly, and though they might come in as guides, and leaders of the Church, yet in time they diſcover themſelves to be ſuch as lead out of the way.</p>
            <p>So you ſee who they are that the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, under the denomination of houſe-creepers; I ſhall now make ſome application, <hi>USE</hi> 1. This ſheweth us the evil of thoſe who are ready to make a bad uſe of this Scripture, and from this do endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to caſt reproach on all ſuch that do aſſemble together out of neceſſity, and wait on God in, his ordinances in private places. What ground have they to make this as their main battery againſt ſuch? Surely they bewray their ignorance and malice herein. 1. Their ignorance, not rightly conſidering the Scripture, and that it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Were this rightly underſtood, they might be eaſily convinced, that there is no ground from Scripture to charge men with evil on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Alas Chriſt, whom they will profeſs to be their Maſter, was frequent in this manner of preaching; he taught in a Ship on the Mount, in the Houſe, and ſeveral other places. And the Apoſtle;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104103:12"/>of Chriſt, who were the Miniſters of Chriſt, and followed him, and thoſe, whom many of them do profeſs themſelves to be their ſucceſſours and ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, were frequent in this. And therefore it muſt needs be a thing which is good and juſt, that the Word of God doth juſtifie. Yea, Chriſt hath left it on record, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, &amp;c.</hi> It is ſad therefore to caſt ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and reproach on perſons, for doing that which was done by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that were left by him to be guides unto the Church. For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am of Chriſt.</hi> Now where we have the example of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> concurring with the example of Chriſt, it ill becomes men to caſt ſlaunders on any; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they have been inſtruments of forcing men to private places. It is very well known, that many in this our Nation, on whom this is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly charged, have been in as publick places as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, and defired as diligently to attend the work that God called them unto. But when ſuch impoſitions were put on them, that they could not yeild unto without manifeſt wrong done unto their conſciences; it was their great grief, and the grief of thoſe that had benefit by their Miniſtry, that their mouthes were ſtopt. And therefore when it pleaſed God to put this into the heart of his Majeſty to give them this indulgence, they were ready to embrace it with all thankfulneſs to God and man. So that now their aſſemblies ought not to be called private but publick, where all may have acceſs, even thoſe that charge them on this account, to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104103:12"/>what they aſſert and hold forth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their malice and bitterneſs. For you may ſay, why, this is ſtrange, if the Apoſtle doth not here condemn all that preach privately, what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that they ſhould be ſo bitter againſt it? Why truly friends, that lieth in their own breaſts, their reaſons are beſt known to themſelves: we are not to judge of ſecrets, it hath been commonly affirmed, that they in private places have aſſerted ſeditious principles. But I may certainly conclude, that thoſe that ſtick not to utter ſuch injurious ſlaunders, did they conſult with their own conſciences, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would clear them on this account. But it is moſt certain, that the people of God ought not to practice any thing in Gods worſhip, but what they know is warranted from the Word, and this is the duty of Miniſters, to teſtify and exhort here unto. And though they would ſuggeſt diſloyalty, yet they themſelves when they are croſſed in their deſigns, ſhew malice and bitterneſs enough.</p>
            <p>The Lord will one day open the eyes of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to ſee, that thoſe that are moſt faithfull to God are moſt faithfull to men, and thoſe that are moſt faithfull to God will give men their due, though they do not put them in the place of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE.</hi> 2. This ſhould teach people to take heed how they take up ſlaunderous reports from whomſoever they hear them, but that they be carefull to examine things, and compare them with the Word of God. For you ſee, the ſame men that the Apoſtle calleth creepers into houſes (which I ſhewed you might be meant of ſuch that preach never ſo openly) the ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104103:13"/>men, I ſay, <hi>v.</hi> 13. He calleth <hi>evil men and ſeducers.</hi> The Scripture giveth us this rule, <hi>to try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> Some people through their ignorance are offenced, and look on it as evil for any to preach the Word, and wait on the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God in any places, but in thoſe that are conſecrated and ſet apart for that uſe, becauſe they read that it was uſually at the Temple and Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, they think that it muſt be there and no where elſe; and theſe places are holy places. But theſe are miſtakes ariſing from ignorance; they do not underſtand that the Temple was called holy, not becauſe there was any inherent holineſs in it ſelf. But</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe there were the viſible ſignes of Gods Preſence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Temple was a Figure of Chriſt, and in that reſpect was called holy, as you may ſee by thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and I will build it in three days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Temple was a ſhadow of the Church of God, to ſhew us, that as in the Temple were the viſible ſignes of Gods Preſence, ſo in the Church of God, which is the ſpiritual Temple, God dwelleth by his Spirit. But now you may take notice, that ſince theſe types and ſhadows are aboliſhed, there is no ſuch difference of places; for Chriſt telleth us, <hi>That not at this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>but whereſoever men call on the Father in ſpirit and in truth, there he will be found.</hi> Beſides, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that in that time, when the Temple was the Place appointed of God for Publick Worſhip, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104103:13"/>ſuch things under the Law to be done there, which ought not to be done elſewhere (ſo that if there were Holineſs in any place, it was in the Temple) yet in this time Chriſt himſelf preached in ſeveral other places, and ſo did the Apoſtles afterwards. So that it is Mens ignorance to think, that the ſame Duties performed in one place were more holy, then if they were performed in another, and it is a great fault to take up prejudices againſt perſons on this account. Again, there are ſome that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried forth through raſh and intemperate zeal and bitterneſs of ſpirit, againſt perſons on this account, (and it may be inſtigated by the ſubtilty of others) but if this hath been the Practice of Chriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Chriſt himſelf; and if Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his Preſence, not only in this place, and that place, but whereſoever his people meet together in his Name, then let perſons take heed how they ſet themſelves againſt Chriſt, that they be not found Fighters againſt God: for let them be ſure, what Chriſt alloweth his people in, in that he will juſtifie them; and in what Chriſt hath given them his example, and what he hath promiſed his bleſſing to, there he will ſurely make it good. So that theſe, though in their intemperate zeal, they think, as the Jews did in their oppoſition of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that they did do God good ſervice, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are miſtaken; for believe it, thoſe men that have the warrant of Chriſt for what they do, Chriſt will bear them out at that great day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and when men ſhall come to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count why they have done ſuch and ſuch things; it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104103:14"/>will not be a ſufficient ground to ſay becauſe others did ſo, and they did it out of their zeal; Chriſt will juſtiſte thoſe that have his Word for their warrant, but how dreadfull will it be for thoſe at the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt, that are charged with this, that they have oppoſed his ſervants for imitating him.</p>
            <p>USE. 3. It ſheweth the evil of thoſe that cry out ſo much, and render perſons as evil doers, which were themſelves and their own ways examined, it would be found who they are, that are moſt juſtly to be charged with this in my text. There are ſome that exclaim againſt others, as corner Preachers and houſe Preachers, when if their own ways were well examined, they would hardly clear themſelves. Who will be found ſuch at laſt, either thoſe that are forced into ſecret places, and notwithſtanding are willing that their Doctrines ſhould be put to the tryal; or ſuch that preaching publickly will be offended, when their Doctrines are tryed and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined? Did men ſeek after ſecret places, that their Doctrines might be concealed, there were a ground of ſuſpicion, but ſuch as are willing to have their Doctrines tryed, and do not ſhun the light, they may not properly be called houſe-creepers. Should men deal with them, as the <hi>Bereans</hi> with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> they would be looked upon as cenſorious, and men of factious and proud ſpirits, meerly becauſe they do their duty in examining mens Doctrines by the Word of God, for which the Apoſtle commendeth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104103:14"/>the <hi>Bereans Acts</hi> 17. <hi>that they ſearched the Scripture to ſee whether theſe things were ſo or no.</hi> Can ſuch be juſtly charged with Hereſy, that are willing that thoſe things which they hold forth ſhould be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Scripture? This is it which they ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly call for, <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi> who do you think would moſt ſeek a corner, if theſe things were well weighed and conſidered, either thoſe that preſſe things on humane authority; or thoſe that preſſe things on Divine authority? Thoſe that cannot endure to have their Doctrines tryed do give great ground of ſuſpicion: Perſons may pretend much to holyneſs but this is no part of their holyneſs to held forth ſuch things that are not juſtifiable from the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Certainly thoſe perſons that are willing to have whatſoever they deliver, examined and tryed by thoſe that have the ſharpeſt ſpirit of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, (alwaies provided that they make the Word of God the ſtandard to try by, and not the Lawes of men) thoſe, I ſay that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have it ſo done, are not to be accounted houſe-creepers. And as for ſuch that have the warrant of Gods Word for what they do, Chriſt will bear them out, notwithſtanding the ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and falſe imputations of men. You know what anſwer Chriſt gave the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when they quarrelled with him concerning his Diſciples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not obſerve ſuch and ſuch traditions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104103:15"/>This is that that will bear men out at the great day of Account, when they can plead Gods Command and Inſtitution for what they do. When God put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth men this Queſtion, <hi>Who required this at your hands?</hi> What horrour will ſeize on their hearts, when they cannot ſay, Lord, we have thy word for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE</hi> 4 Since the Apoſtle telleth us that ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are dangerous perſons, let us take heed; for it is a matter of great weight and concernment. The Apoſtle would never have taken ſo much care to warn us, he would not have ſet forth the danger of it, had it not been a matter of great moment Let us then take heed, that we are not deceived by ſuch kind of perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But you will ſay how ſhall we know them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANS.</hi> There is a great ground of ſuſpicion, when in times of peace and liberty, that men may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger, or moleſtation hold forth the truth, when, I ſay, in ſuch times they will out of choice take private places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve what the drift of their doctrine is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. <hi>Beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try their ſpirits;</hi> And how? <hi>By their doctrine.</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what it is that their doctrine tendeth to, That which doth derogate from Chriſt and give unto the Creature; which doth derogate from the grace and glory of Chriſt, and advance the Creature; that is moſt corrupt and unſound: when mens doctrine rendeth to this, to ſet up any thing of man, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt mans free-will and works of righteouſneſs, as if there were ſomething in that, which might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104103:15"/>us acceptable unto God, this is very dangerous. When men derogate from Chriſt, when they do not make Chriſt the only way to ſalvation, (for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Neither is their ſalvation in any other, for there is none other name, &amp;c.</hi>) When they derogate from the free grace of God, they are ſuch indeed that are of this kind of creepers, and deceivers that are here ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Again, look to this, whether their Doctrine be ſuch, that doth hold forth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be the ſole Governour, and Head of the Church: thoſe that will impoſe on men ſuch a worſhip, as is not grounded on the Word, are thoſe that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh of.</p>
            <p>So thoſe perſons that do not clearly hold forth the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and preſs men to look off from all other things, and reſt on Chriſt only for life and ſalvation: that do not preſs men to live by faith on Chriſt, are perſons that do erre from the truth, and ſo far as their Doctrine prevaileth they lead from the truth.</p>
            <p>So when men take off the affections of people, from holyneſs and puerity of converſation, they are ſuch whoſe Doctrine is corrupt and unſound; for we ought to preſs people to manifeſt the power of faith in a holy and unblameable converſation. Now theſe things we ſhhold look unto, and try them by the Word of God, according to that <hi>Iſ.</hi> 8.20. and Chriſt telleth us, that by their fruits we ſhall know them. Now ſome fruit of a Miniſter is his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE</hi> 5. May perſons come under this denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104103:16"/>though never ſo publick, then let none think themſelves ſafe, this is that which many poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do deceive themſelves with; oh, think they, we are ſafe enough from any ſeduction and leading aſide, we never go to ſuch places. Others run on an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other extream, they will not go to publick places, they diſlike all that is ſpoken there, but this is evil on the other hand, we are not to judge of truth by places, but as God approveth it, and as it is grounded on the Scripture. For in a great concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple we may be led aſide from the truth, neither do ſecret places give us any ſecurity, but there we may be led aſide from the truth. Let us then bring the Doctrines we hear to the touch-ſtone of Gods Word, and not to reject them, becauſe publique, neither applaud them, meerly becauſe private, and ſo on the other hand. Thoſe that are ſo rigorous againſt private places, what would they have done, if they had lived in the dayes of Chriſt? they would have rejected Chriſt and his Doctrine, becauſe he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a Mountaine, and in a Ship; and if they had lived in the dayes of the Apoſtles, they would have done the like. A faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt, whether private or publick, will endeavour to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf to God, by holding forth ſuch things as are conſonant and agreeable to the Word of God. Truth may be private, when errour may be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as in the dayes of <hi>Ahab,</hi> when ſome of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were impriſoned, and ſome put to death, and <hi>Jezeebel</hi> had four hundred Prophets of <hi>Baal</hi> that fed daily at her table, theſe at that time had the publick
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104103:16"/>places, and ſo in the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles I proceed now to the ſecond obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OB.</hi> That ſuch perſons uſually effect their deſign on ſuch as are either weak and ignorant, not able to diſcern their corrupt and unſound Doctrine; or ſuch as are under the power of ſome baſe luſt or luſts, be they men or women; for it may be underſtood of both ſexes, ſuch being by the juſt judgment of God left to themſelves, and ſo they eaſily prevail on them. Obſerve what <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.15. <hi>The ſimple beleeveth every thing, but the prudent look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well to his goings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doth he mean in that, but this? A man that is ſimple and void of underſtanding; you may make him beleeve any thing, if you put a fair gloſſe and colour upon it, but a man of underſtanding will lift and try and examine, and ſee what grounds there are for the Doctrine that is delivered. Of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. Now here.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſhew you that they uſually effect their deſigned on perſons that are ignorant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they alſo effect their deſign on thoſe that are under the power of ſome luſt or luſts, that are in bondage to ſome baſe luſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That God in his juſt judgment is pleaſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to give over ſuch to be ſeduced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That their deſign is uſually effected on thoſe that are ignorant of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>This you may ſee if you look into the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104103:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Scripture. Who were they among the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the falſe Prophets did ſo eaſily draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide? you may ſee they were any ſuch that did not know the Lord. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.3.4, 5. Now how came this to paſs? They were led aſide, and ſeduced by thoſe falſe Prophets that <hi>Jeremiah</hi> complaineth of, that did deceive them, and ſpeaking ſmooth things to them, did harden and confirm them in their evil wayes. Again, you may ſee how they were drawn in <hi>Jeroboams</hi> time to that groſſe and abominable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry; they willingly walked after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.11. Now what people were theſe? the Prophet telleth us <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>they were ſuch as were without the knowledge of God,</hi> where there is no knowledge of God in a Land, people, are eaſily crawn aſide into the moſt pernicious errours. And what was the reaſon that the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> had ſo many followers, and ſo few followed Chriſt? Why the people were ignorant of the Law, and the <hi>Phariſees</hi> by their groſſe and corrupt interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did deceive them. They were a people that did not know the Law, if they had known the Word of God, Chriſt and the truths of Chriſt would have been very precious to them. And what was the cauſe in this Nation in former dayes, and with other Nations that remain under Ponery, they are drawn aſide to embrace the moſt-abominable errours, to beleeve things that are ſo groſſely corrupt? It is becauſe they are without the Word, the Scriptures are locked up in an unknown language, and people without the Word do beleeve any thing though never ſo groſſe. Do you think, that abſurd and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104103:17"/>abominable opinion of the Popiſh Maſſe would be received, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Bread and Wine is the very Body and Blood of Chriſt? Alſo that Croſſing themſelves with their Fingers is that which will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them from evil, (and many the like fooliſh opinions) if people were not ignorant of the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which <hi>I</hi> am to ſhew you further is this. That as ignorant perſons are apt to be drawn aſide to errours, ſo likewiſe thoſe that live under the power of ſome luſt or luſts, Conſider that <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. The time that the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaketh of, was a time of looſneſs and prophaneneſs. They did what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was good in their own eyes; v 5. The great men had ſome knowledge of God, but notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had burſt the yoke, and broken the bonds, they would not be under the power of Gods Word, but would walk according to their own luſts &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Likewiſe that in <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.16. When the Word that <hi>Jere.</hi> had ſpoken in the name of the Lord croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their luſts, ſee how ſtubbornly they anſwer. As for the VVord which thou haſt ſpoken to us in the Name of the Lord, we will not hearken to thee. VVhen perſons are under the power of any luſt, they are in a ready way to be ſeduced to any thing, though never ſo corrupt. VVhen men are in love with any ſin, and do wilfully retain any luſt, they are fit perſons for ſeducers to work upon. And u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually ſuch perſons with whom the fleſh and their own carnal intereſt prevailes, have been drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from following the truth, though they have lived ſome time under a profeſſion of it, and have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104103:18"/>had ſome knowledge of it, I ſay, ſuch perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overſwayed by their luſts, have been turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from the truths which they formerly embraced, into the moſt corrupt and abominable ways. We have had experience of it in this our Nation, when God was pleaſed to give us peace and plenty, and all that our hearts could deſire; how many were there that lived under a Profeſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when Religion was in credit; yet the World having the Maſtery of their hearts, how ſuddenly did thoſe perſons miſcarry and turn aſide, ſome to one opinion, and ſome to another? And ſurely, thoſe who lie in wait to deceive, obſerve the frame and temper of mens ſpirits, and order their deceits accordingly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That God in his juſt judgment giveth ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be deceived. VVhen once men will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge themſelves in any way of ſin; when once they wilfully take up their reſolutions, that they will do ſo and ſo, though it be expreſſely contrary to the VVord of God. God is pleaſed to give ſuch over to deluſions, 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould believe a Lie.</hi> For what cauſe? becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved. Obſerve, that he doth not ſay, that they did not receive the truth, but they received not the love of the truth, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> though they had ſome illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and ſome knowledge of the truth, yet they had not the love of the truth in their hearts, they did not receive it as from God, and ſo ſubject themſelves unto it, but their hearts did riſe againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104103:18"/>it, becauſe it croſſed their luſts and wills. Now God in his juſt judgment doth give ſuch over to beleeve a lye. This you may take notice of, that where God is graciouſly pleaſed to afford means of knowledge to a people, and that people do either ſlight it and take little notice of it, or elſe content themſelves in a bare external profeſſion, and do not receive it in love and ſubmiſſion, God is pleaſed ſometime to give ſuch over to be very corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and to embrace errours contrary to thoſe truths that formerly they have received; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have there been in theſe times lately paſt, that have lived under a profeſſion, and ſeemed very zealous and forward; and yet ſome corruption ſwaying their hearts, they have not only fallen off from that fervour in the Ordinances of God, but have looked on them as below their attainments, and as needleſs things to them, and look on the vaine fancies and conceits that ariſe in their mindes to be the breathings and moveings of the Spirit of God, and at laſt, caſt off all ſhew of Religion, and queſtion whether there be any Religion or God, yea or no? Now conſider this, what a ſad and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing is this, to fall into ſuch deluſions? and yet how many were there of thoſe whom God was pleaſed thus to give over, whom one would have thought ſhould never have received ſuch things as theſe in their hearts? But it hath been evident by fad and wofull experience; and this indeed is not to be admired at; but we may rather marvel that it is not general amongſt us, conſidering
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104103:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>how we have ſlighted the Gods Word, and denyed the power of it in our lives: God is pleaſed once more to give us this liberty, that we ſhould openly enjoy his Ordinances; Let us remember that God will not ſuffer ſuch mercys to be abuſed. It is high time for us to look to our ſelves, to labour to know the mind and will of God, and knowing it to embrace it with affection and obedience. If we know not the things that belong to our peace in the day of our viſitation, we cannot expect but that the iſſue will be ſad, that God may judicially give men over to a ſpirit of deluſion, that they ſhall run into the moſt dreadfull and erroneous opinions, and all kind of groſſe and idolatrous ſuperſtitions and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>And thus we have cleared the point the grounds follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe ignorant perſons, through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and blindneſs of their underſtandings are not able to judge and try things, and to put difference between things that differ. Men that know not truth from errour, may be eaſily deceived, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when there is an outward ſhew, and fair gloſſe put upon it. A man may eaſily be overcome in Combate that is diſcovered, or that hath no skill to uſe his armes. Many men live without Gods Word, and though they have it, do not know how to manage this Sword of the Spirit, (as it is called by the Apoſtle) they know not how to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor to offend thoſe that aſſault them. And Satan (is he is eſpecially ſubtill) ſo his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have learned this policy of him; when they hear men
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104103:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>pleading Scripture, and obſerve their unskil fullneſs in the Scriptures; they will plead Scripture too. As now for defence of the Doctrine of merit, by good works, that by theſe men might be made worthy and obtaine eternal life, this Scripture will be ſtrongly pleaded 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18.19. Look here, ſay they, it is clear and evident, that we ought to lay up good works in ſtore for our ſelves, as a good foundation, by virtue of which we may obtain eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life. But the falſhood of this is eaſily diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if we look to the 17. v. Charge them that are rich in this world that they be not high minded, nor truſt in uncertain riches. Charge them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y plead th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they are beleevers, and that they be not high minded, they are apt ſince they beleeve in God, it ſhall be well enough with them. But let them ſhew their faith by their fruitfullneſs in good works, let their faith be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in their practice, eſpecially in their readineſs to releeve the diſtreſſed members of Chriſt; for this is that which Chriſt will take eſpeciall notice of before the whole world. Wherefore we muſt not ſo underſtand the Apoſtle, as if by this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (Laying up in ſtore for themſelves) were meant the merit of good works, which give us right to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life; but that it might be evident that they are ſuch as have beleeved in Chriſt, by their fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs in good works: for where the Spirit of God is in the heart, that Spirit teacheth a beleever to manifeſt the efficacy of his faith in a godly life and converſation, and in a readineſs to diſtribute to the neceſſitous members of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe that place <hi>Col.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That ye might walk worthy of the Lord &amp;c.</hi> Now ſay they, how ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104103:20"/>we walk worthy? and what is our worthineſs but by way of reward? But that which the Apoſtle calls worthineſs, is no more then ſuitableneſs and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Giving thanks unto the Father which hath made us meet to be Partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> Now how are we made meet and worthy? ſurely not by any thing in us, but by Chriſt only, as the next words ſhew, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. So that we are not made meet by any works of our own, but we come to be made meet by being clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from our ſins, and clothed in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, by being taken out of <hi>Adam</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted into Chriſt; and ſo having received the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, we are made meet to be Partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light. There is a ſuitableneſs in this life to that heavenly and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, that we ſhall live with God for ever. So that this is an abuſe of Scripture. I might ſhew you that life cannot be obtained by works of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or by any thing that we can do.</p>
            <p>It cannot be by works of charity; for mind that which the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Men may give all their Goods to the poor,</hi> as too many ignorant ſouls have done amongſt the Papiſts. <hi>Nay, men may give their bodies to be burned, but yet if they have not Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> (i. e.) if the love of God be not ſhed abroad in their hearts, and the work be not done from a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of love, it is unacceptable. Mind alſo that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>By grace ye are ſaved through faith, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, works have no hand, no ſhare at all in this great work.</p>
            <p>Again, they abule that place, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>our father juſtified by works?</hi> here to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their Juſtification by works, they bring the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104103:20"/>ſame Argument that the Apoſtle brought in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe. The ſame way that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſame way are all the faithful juſtified. But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was juſtified by works, therefore by works are all the faithful juſtified; But compare this with <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>believed God, and it was counted to him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi> What was counted? why that which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> believed in and reſted on, that is, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt; but it was before men only, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by works; for we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God, and the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before men; ſo that in confounding theſe lieth the ſubtilty of the adverſary. Now on this account they will bring Scripture; &amp; poor people that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and unskilful in the Word of God, when they hear a man bring Scripture to confirm his errors. Oh ſay they, he proved it out of Scripture, though it be directly contrary to Gods Word. Likewiſe they bring that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. <hi>For I was hungry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is as clear as the Sun, that that place is not to be ſo underſtood, as if their works were the cauſe why Chriſt did bring them to glory; but thoſe works were mention'd as fruits and effects of faith, which were evident to all; faith it ſelf is ſecret and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to none but God himſelf, but works are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to all, and therefore it was meet that Chriſt paſſing a ſentence of Acquittance and Abſolution on them ſhould recite it to all, even as a Judge doth recite all that by which the perſon is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; ſo Chriſt doth here, ſhewing that their faith is not a dead faith, but a living ſaith that did work by love, and carried them to obedience to God, ſo that this is in reſpect of their Juſtification before the whole world.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104103:21"/>
            <p>Again, they will urge Scripture as for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worſhip, yea, though they have no Word of God for it; yet they will tell you, that their Ceremonies are for the beautifying and adorning of the Church, and for decency in the Worſhip of God; that things are not to be done confuſedly but in order. Whereas indeed thoſe things are moſt orderly that we have Chriſts Word for, and that is moſt decent that Chriſt thinketh moſt fit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; for Chriſt, being the Lord of the Houſe, that is decent which he appointeth in the Houſe, But alas! Men when they hear a Scripture produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, though they do not conſider the thing that is there intended, yet are ſoon ſtartled: and hence are people driven into the moſt abominable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: As for inſtance, to receive that abhorred Doctrine of the Popiſh Maſs. Why, ſay the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, doth not Chriſt expreſſely ſay, <hi>This is my Body?</hi> And is not Chriſt the Author of truth? And ought we to queſtion any thing that Chriſt hath ſaid? Whenas Chriſt ſpeaketh figuratively, that the Bread and Wine were figures, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent ſpiritually the Body and Blood of Chriſt. Chriſt ſpeaketh Sacramentally, and by way of a Figure, that is uſual in the Scriptures, as ſometimes Chriſt calleth himſelf <hi>A Door,</hi> and <hi>A Vine.</hi> So is Circumciſion called <hi>A Covenant.</hi> And God ſaith, that thoſe that were Circumciſed had broke his Covenant, becauſe Circumciſion was the ſign of the Covenant. So that it cannot be the meaning of Chriſt, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould intend that the Bread and Wine was his natural Body and Blood, for he was then alive and viſible before his diſciples.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104103:21"/>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe their doctrine doth ſuit to the corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption that is in mens hearts. Now thoſe that we are ſpeaking of are not able to ſee the evil, and the ſtrong inclinations of their h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts to that which is evil; but being that which doth ſuit to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt hearts, therefore they receive it. For herein lieth the difference between the Miniſters of Chriſt and falſe teachers: The Miniſters of Chriſt hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the truths of Chriſt, have nothing of Man to lay hold on, for corrupt doctrine doth ſuit with corrupt natures: ſuch a doctrine as this is, to extol Juſtification by VVorks, or at leaſt that works have ſome ſhare in it, this doth exceedingly take with corrupt hearts.</p>
            <p>Alſo to worſhip God after the Inventions of Men, and to frame a manner of worſhip of our own: this is that which mens hearts are in love withal, they think that by this they deſerve at Gods Hand: and ſuch corrupt doctrines they will drink in as ſweet wine, though in the end they will find it a bitter poiſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe they are ignorant, and not able to underſtand the great danger that is in ſuch corrupt doctrine, how much it tendeth to the diſhonour of God, and how greatly it provoketh the Lord-Thoſe that are ignorant do little think, that the ſetting up Mans works in the point of Juſtification, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly affront the Divine Majeſty, ſuch ſlight the Love of God in the Gift of his Son: for if we are able to juſtifie our ſelves, what need have we of Chriſt? Chriſt is alſo exceedingly provoked by ſetting up the rags of their own righteouſneſs as Co-Partners with his righteouſneſs, nay, to ſet it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104103:22"/>above the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, this is that which doth exceedingly provoke him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh to ſuch in the Name of Chriſt. <hi>This ye ſhall have at my hands, ye ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi> They render the Spirit of God a Liar, who when he hath declared that there is no ſalvation in any other, but in Chriſt alone; and that this is the great deſign of God, that he will magnifie his own grace and abaſe man, that no fleſh ſhall glory in his ſight. I ſay, they give a lie to the Spirit of God who aſſert their own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs for Juſtification. Again, they do not know the danger of the corrupt mixture of the devices of men with the Juſtitutions of Chriſt; they know not what danger it is to oppoſe Chriſt in his own houſe, wherof he is the Lord: theſe men knew it not. Therefore they are adviſed, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2 <hi>to kiſs the Son.</hi> I tell you, to go to diſenthrone Chriſt, and to rule in his houſe, is another thing then men are aware of. Thus you ſee the reaſon, why ignorant perſons are ſo eaſily ſeduced and drawn into errour.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons why they prevail on ſuch that are in bondage under ſome luſt or luſts may be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they ſuit their doctrines to the luſts of men, that harden their hearts, and ſtrengthen their hands in their iniquities, that is the reaſon why cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrine is embraced by ſuch. The falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſaw well enough, that <hi>Ahab</hi> had a mind to go up to <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> and they had a minde to pleaſe <hi>Ahab: Oh,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Go up and proſper. So</hi> thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s time ſaw that the people had a good mind to live looſely and prophanely, but they were terrified by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prophet <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> ſee how
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104103:22"/>they ſuit their doctrine to their luſts. <hi>Peace ſhall be unto you: What think ye that God will bring in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the upon you that are his people? that God will deſtroy his Temple?</hi> And thus it is with the ſubtile J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſuits, they carry on their ways ſo, that they foſter m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in their wickedneſs, though they have a ſhew of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, yet they know how to indulge men in their ſinful luſts and liberties, they have deviſed ways for it, that according to their principles men may live looſely and licentiouſly, and yet all may be well enough with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They uſually prevail with ſuch, becauſe ſuch as theſe have their hearts ſet on their luſts. As for inſtance, thoſe whoſe hearts are ſet on the world, they are reſolved to encreaſe in the world, they will rather part with Chriſt then their covetouſneſs. You know how it was with the young man in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, he would have Chriſt and his riches too, and ſo it is with many, they are willing to have Heaven and the world too: but if they muſt part with one of them, they will part with any thing rather then with their luſt. The covetous mans Gold, the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious mans vain glory command their hearts and conſciences: they will rather condeſcend to any thing though contrary to their own principles, then part with their luſts. And therefore it is no wonder if ſuch perſons miſcarry.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why God doth give ſuch over to be deluded, is becauſe they reject the truth, as in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>They received not the love of the truth, they loved not the truth, they embraced it not with their hearts;</hi> it follows, <hi>God ſhal ſend them ſtrong deluſion.</hi> When men pleaſe themſelves in any ſinful way, and there reſt, its a dangerous condition, and God in his juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104103:23"/>may give ſuch over to be deceived. You know how it was with <hi>Ahab:</hi> the Prophets told him he ſhould go up and proſper; but when <hi>Micajah</hi> came he ſet the truth before him, but his luſts liked it not, his pride and ambition and his deſire to enlarge his territories cauſed him to hate <hi>Micajah.</hi> When men have had the truth ſet before them, and have been convinced thereof, and their underſtandings ſomewhat inlightned, and yet they have neglected this light, God may in his juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment let darkneſs overſpread their underſtandings, God may ſay thus to ſuch a ſoul. Seeing thou wilt not beleeve the truth thou ſhalt beleeve a lye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE</hi> 1. This gives us to ſee the ſad condition of all thoſe that are ignorant of Gods Word, that are not able to diſcern between truth and errour, between the mind of God and the groſſe conceits of Satan and his inſtruments. It muſt needs be dangerous in theſe laſt times, if you conſider theſe Scriptures. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.11. <hi>Many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe and deceive many.</hi> What a ſad and dreadfull thing is it, that when falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, when they ſhall come and ſay, here is Chriſt, and there is Chriſt, and yet he is not among either? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>There ſhall be ſuch that ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies.</hi> What a ſad condition then I ſay, muſt ſuch ſoules be in, that live in ſuch times, when ſuch pernicious ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are abroad, and they are not able to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween truth and errour. You would ſay that that man were in a ſad condition, that did ſet forth ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things of great value to ſell, and a multitude did flock about him with falſe Coyn, and he were not able to diſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> between what was good and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104103:23"/>what was falſe; every one that did ſee him would ſay, that man will be utterly undone. So it is here, what a ſad condition is this? when men ſhall come with corrupt and unſound Doctrine, and ſhall deceive them, and they are not able to diſcern the precious truths of Chriſt from thoſe damnable Doctrines? Alas! in what a condition are the ignorant, when men ſhall come after this manner to them, and tell them, that by their improvement of their natural abilities, and that common light which God hath given them, they ſhall obtain the love and favour of God, and ſhall in time come to partake of everlaſting life and glory? What a dreadfull thing is this? and yet this goeth down currant with thoſe that doe not know the Scripture, when it is manifeſt that we are dead, and that the light that is in us is groſſe darkneſs, that unleſs he that is the light of light doth inlighten us by the light of his bleſſed ſpirit, we are never able to diſcern ſpirituall things. So when men come and tell them that by their good works, by their repentance and works of righteouſneſs they may do away their ſins and obtain Gods favour. When men do bring theſe things with fair gloſſes and pretences, colouring them with the Scripture, they are eaſily carried away with them. Oh, ſay they, theſe are good men, they bring the Word of God for what they ſay.</p>
            <p>Again, if they come with ſuch Doctrine as this, that men ought not to ruſh preſently into the preſence of Chriſt; but they muſt make friends by ſome Mediators; as by the Saints that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and by this means they may be interceded for, that they may be heard of him. Oh, ſay they, this doth not derogate from the honour of Chriſt, he hath the honour of all we do; But it is rudeneſs thus to ruſh immediately into his preſence. This carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far with ignorant people; for here is a fair pretence and ſhiew of humility, though it is clear in the Scriptures, that they bring a great deale of diſhonour to Chriſt, when they take away the honour of his Mediatorſhip; and put it on Saints and Angels. We cannot diſhonour Chriſt more, then when we rob him of the glory of his grace, incouraging us at all times to come to him; and that we ſhould come to the Father in and through the Son. It is not for the ſake of Saints and Angels, but for the ſake of Chriſt alone that we are accepted of God.</p>
            <p>Again, when they bring ſuch abomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e Doctrine as this, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104103:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>we muſt pray before Images. Oh, ſay they, we pray not to the Images, but theſe are ſerviceable to keep our affections on God, whereas they place a holyneſs in ſuch things, and make that a help which God hath not commanded but expreſſly forbidden.</p>
            <p>And what a ſad thing is it, when ſoules are drawn aſide to embrace ſuch impious Doctrine as this; that after the words of conſcecration, the bread is the very Body of Chriſt? and argue thus. This is the Word of Chriſt, that is truth himſelf, and will you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt? Again, others that are not ſo horribly groſſe have other ways to deceive, preſſing men to worſhip God after another way then that which God hath appointed. If you ask them what ground they have for ſuch and ſuch needleſs cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: Why, ſay they, this is decency; and we muſt do all things decently and in order. Alas! how many poor ſoules are deceived herein, and become zealous contenders for Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and more earneſt in them then in the things that God hath commanded? Many are ſo zealous and intemperate, that they will admit of no worſhip but this, and look on Diſeenters as factions and ſeditious that will not yeild unto them.</p>
            <p>Again, there is nothing that the nature of man is more apt to be carried aſide in, then to advance ſomething of himſelf, and to ſet up his own righteouſneſs, and there is no way ſo ſubtil as this to deceive poor ſouls, who will ſay, Loe this man is for good works, for ſerving God. Is not this a good man? Friends, it is a good thing to be found in works of righteouſneſs, but if you reſt on works of righteouſneſs, as thoſe that may render you accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, thinking your ſelves to be juſtified by them in the ſight of God, there is nothing more dangerous; it is a dreadfull thing for a man to eſtabliſh his own righteouſneſs, it is more dangerous then all the Images in the world: ſee what Chriſt ſaith to the <hi>Phariſees, Mat.</hi> 21, 30.31. Now what is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt in that Parable? Chriſt ſetteth forth thoſe Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Harlots, that walked directly againſt the commands of God, to be thoſe that ſaid they would not. They are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but they obſtinately anſwer, We will not. Then he ſpeaketh to the <hi>Jewes</hi> that profeſſed obedience and ſubmiſſion to the Law of God. Do you what <hi>I</hi> command you. We will, ſay they, they had a profeſſion, and they thought to juſtifie themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. But Chriſt ſaith, the Publicans and Harlots go into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104103:24"/>the Kingdome of God before you. And why ſo? becauſe theſe were convinced as being open profeſſed enemies againſt God, and therefore could not eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, when as the <hi>Jewes</hi> living under a profeſſion contented themſelves therewith and ſought to advance their own righteouſneſs, and ſo ſubmitted not to the righteouſneſs which is of God. So <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11 12. The Phariſee ſaith, <hi>God I thank thee &amp;c. But the Publican ſtood afar off and ſmote on his breaſt,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>The Lord be mercyfull to me a ſinner &amp;c. I</hi> cannot ſay, <hi>I</hi> have done this or that, but this I ſay, that without thy mercy I muſt periſh for ever. Oh it is dreadfull to reſt on our own righteouſneſs: I could ſhew you many ways how greatly the ſins of ſuch are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, It utterly overthrows the great deſign of God. It over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the whole Goſpel, and all that Jeſus Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for. And therfore what a dreadfull thing is it, when poor ſouls are carried away with vain pretences into ſuch an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? Surely ſuch are in a ſad condition, that are not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern truth from errour, but are eaſily carried away with fair words, by which deceivers beguile poor ſouls and make a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> 2. Let us ſee then the great wickedneſs of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that lock up the Scripture from people, which is the key of knowledge. You ſee clearely, that they are ignorant perſons for whom deceivers lay their baits; and that the ignorant are moſt drawn away by ſeducers. They fit and prepare people to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that keep Gods Word from them What an abominable thing is that, and how contrary to the Scriptures, that ignorance is the mother of devotion? It is directly contrary to the Scriptures. We find that this is the complaint of God, <hi>My people periſh for want of knowledge.</hi> Surely it is very groſſe to keep people from the knowledge of the Scriptures, and to perſwade them to reſt meerly on the words of their teachers And what is this but to enſnare them, and keep them in bondage continually? And what do they? and how nearely do they follow theſe wretches that incourage people in their ignorance, and diſcourage them from reading the Scripture talling them that they are to follow their own imployments, &amp; that God expecteth not ſuch at their hands, but that which is required of them is to beleeve their Miniſters? But ſurely this was not ſpoken to the Miniſters, but to the people,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104103:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits &amp;c.</hi> This ſhould be on every ones ſpirit to labour after ſuch a meaſure of knowledge; that they may be able to try ſuch things as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to them, and not to receive thoſe things which are contrary to the mind and will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Use</hi> 3. What cauſe have we to bleſs God in this Nation that have had free liberty of Gods Word? it hath not been locked up to us. Oh that we had wiſdom rightly to improve this mercy; that the Scripture might not be to us as a price put into the hands of fools. Let us be diligent to read and meditate on the Word of God. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are they that read the Word of this Prophecy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> We f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, that all were commanded in the book of the law continually; none was exempted, not ſo much as the King himſelf. And as we ſhould read the Scripture, ſo we ſhould me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on it, that is the bleſſed man indeed that doth meditate on Gods Word day and night. Alſo we ſhould be inſtant in prayer, that God would open our eyes to ſee the marvellous things of his law, we ſhould embrace all opportunities that God gives us to wait on him in his Ordinances, that we might receive inſtruction, and be built up in the faith. Its ſad to be in thoſe places wherein we live, that there ſhould be ſuch groſſe ignorance and darkneſs in mens underſtandings. And how juſt is it with God to give ſuch over to be deceived that are of a dull and careleſs frame of ſpirit? For the Lords ſake conſider ſeriouſly of it, and put it to your own ſoules, what opportunities have you omitted wherein you might have attended on Gods Ordinances? How negligent have you been in reading Gods Word? How juſtly might God give you over to the groſſeſt deluſions, that have made ſo light of ſo precious a word, wherein the wiſdom of God, the grace and love of God ſo eminently appears, wherein there is ſuch incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for poor ignorant ſouls, and for thoſe that find themſelves in a ſtate of miſery and unbeleif to come in and beleeve? And ſee what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> telleth us, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.7. <hi>The law of the Lord is perfect converting the ſoul, the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe the ſimple.</hi> Should ſuch fools be pittied that are fools willingly? Now all that have Gods Word do make themſelves fools in rejecting the means that God hath afforded to make them wiſe. See what <hi>David</hi> ſaith <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. <hi>Thy Word is a light to my waies, and a lanthorn to my paths.</hi> Conſider that God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104103:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>to give to his people a heart that ſhall know him. Who knoweth, how God may in the uſe of his Ordinances ſet home by the power of his ſpirit a word that may ſoften a hard heart, and humble a proud heart; This is the character of Gods people that they are a wiſe underſtanding people If then we would be be of the number of Gods people, let us endeavour afterwiſdom by the improvement of thoſe means that God hath afforded unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Use</hi> 4. Is it ſo that thoſe that live under the power of luſts are the perſons that are deceived by ſeducers? Then conſider what enemies they are to their own ſoules, that do enſnare themſelves under the power of any luſt? they betray themſelves, and lay themſelves open to adverſaries. There is nothing ſo dangerous to a ſoul as that is, that ſets a ſoul in a ready way to be deeived and undone by thoſe that ly in wait to beguile him. We are apt to ſay of ſome ſpecial ſins that our hearts are much ſet upon, this is but a little one: when if we did well conſider and weigh all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, we ſhould find that there is no ſin little, though there are ſom ſins greater then other ſom; yet no ſin can be cal'd little. Now obſerve thoſe that make it their buſineſs to deceive mens ſouls do the frame of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpirits and they know how to fit their baits to mens inclinations. Deceivers are like fiſhers that have for their ſeveral ſorts of Fiſhes their ſeveral baits; when they have to do with men whoſe hearts are ſet on the world, they know how to deal with them there; and when they are lifted up with pride and ambition, they know how to lay a bait to catch them there; and when they ſee that their hearts are filled with the carnal pleaſures of the world, they know how to lay their baits accordingly. And alas! how many are there that have lived under a profeſſion of religion, and yet by giving their hearts an indulgence and tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in ſome luſts, they have betrayed their ſouls into the hands of their adverſaries that ly in wait to deceive them? And theſe ſubtile deceivers, though they fall not on a man to beat him ſuddenly from that which he owneth, yet they intangle his affections till his heart by degrees is taken off, and he is enſnared by them, and comes at length to embrace ſuch abominable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which if they had been preſented to him at the firſt, he would have fled from them as from a Serpent. The Lord graunt that every one of us may conſider of it, for if we regard iniquity in our hearts, and proſtitute our conſciences to the pleaſures of our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104103:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104103:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104103:27"/>luſts, God may juſtly ſuffer us to be ſeduced: wherefore let us make it our buſineſs to purge out every iniquity leſt it be our ruine.</p>
            <p>USE 5. Let us not wonder then, that in ſuch times as we live in there ſhould be ſuch declenſions from the Ways of God. When we ſee times, in which all manner of looſeneſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs reigns, and is not ſuppreſſed; it is no wonder, if thoſe that lie in wait to deceive do proſper in their deſignes; though I do not mean of ſuch that are ſometimes drawn aſide and overcome by their luſts; for God may ſuffer his precious ones to be led aſide for a ſeaſon, but he reſtoreth them again: but when <hi>I</hi> ſay, [ſuch that are under the power of luſt] <hi>I</hi> mean, of ſuch that are ordinarily over-ruled by their luſts, and of that which is the uſual courſe by which corrupt perſons prevail on ſuch. And indeed it is not ſtrange that they prevail on them. As I hinted to you out of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> concerning that groſs Idolatry that was among the people, it was no wonder that the Prophets propheſying lies ſhould prevail on them, for there was horrible prophaneneſs and wickedneſs amongſt them, when corrupt men ſhall frame ſuch a Religion as ſhall ſuit with mens luſts, it is not ſtrange that ſuch men ſhould yield unto them, whoſe hearts are ſet on their luſts. It is not ſtrange, that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery ſhould ſo exceedingly prevail, when they have framed ſuch corrupt ways, that men may go on cheerfully in the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of their luſts. When men ſhall be told that ſome ſins are no ſins, and ſome ſins are venial, and greater ſins may be done away by enduring ſome corporal puniſhments, which alſo it is in he Power of the Prieſt to mitigate; and that if they die in their ſins, they may by enduring ſome puniſhment in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory be purged from their ſins, and afterwards received to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and that it is in the Popes Power to deliver them from theſe pains. If theſe things be well conſidered, we may not wonder that men are ſo eaſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, drawn aſide to groſs Popiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions. Where Chriſt telleth us of <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> he telleth us alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that iniquity ſhall abound, and the love of many ſhall wax old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE 6. This ſhould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>each us to watch our hearts, aud to take eſpecial notice of the corrupt inclinations. Did we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe a way to entangle our ſelves, and enſnare our own ſouls, we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104103:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>could not find a readier way then to ſollow the luſtings of our own hearts. When once the heart is ſet on evil, it taketh of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at the truth, eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cially at ſuch truths that give a wound to its beloved ſins <hi>Herod heard</hi> John Baptiſt <hi>gladly;</hi> but when he toucheth him in his beloved ſin, he heareth him no more. So there are many that make a Profeſſion of Religion, who, when they come to be touched in their beloved ſins, cannot digeſt ſuch plain dealing, and by this means their affections do abate to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and at laſt they fall off, and are willing to joyn in any way that may indulge them in their ſuſts. Therefore that word of <hi>Solomon</hi> is not unſuitable, <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence, &amp;c.</hi> We muſt ſee that we do not allow our ſelves in any evil, one ſin bringeth in another, and frequency of ſinning cauſeth dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and deadneſſe of heart taketh off the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from the Ordinances of God, till by degrees it com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th to have bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit, and deadly enmity againſt thoſe that go on in the practice of thoſe things that are allowable by the Word of God. We have ſeen ſad examples of this kind in theſe our days, how many have been enſnared by the world, rather then they would loſe their honour and eſteem with men, they leave the honour that Chriſt hath tendered to them. Let us not then be ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to our own ſouls.</p>
            <p>USE 7 What cauſe have ſuch that have been preſerved from Apoſtacy and Seduction, to acknowledge the in finite goodneſſe of God unto them? there is none of us, but if we would make a diligent ſearch into our own hearts, our Conſciences will tell us, that ſince we have come to the knowledge of the truth, we have ſinned againſt our own light; we have done thoſe things which our Conſciences have told us we ſhould not have done; how might God have ſuffered us to be deceived and carried aſide to thoſe ways that lead to eternal deſtruction? It is ſad to look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the world, and to ſee how many in theſe times have been carried aſide from the Truths of God, by that corrupt and abominable errour of Popiſh Merit, to eſtabliſh their own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and ſome have been carried aſide to the ſame evil un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of the improvement of their natural parts and abilities, and have ſet up their own work and denied Chriſt? How many have deſpiſed the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inances of God? How many have fallen from their Profeſſion to downright Atheiſm?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104103:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>That it is not ſo with us is becauſe God hath preſerved us and watched over us, how ſhould this engage our hearts to that God that hath made his Word good to us, in keeping us to himſelf by his mighty power through faith.</p>
            <p>And again, let us not wonder that many ſhould be drawn to this opinion, and that opinion; but rather wonder that to this day we have not been ſo deceived. If God ſhould leave us and withdraw from any of us, if God ſhould ſay to any ſoul here, go in thy own way, and beleeve what thou wilt, and embrace what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy heart is ſet upon; what opinion is there? Nay what dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hereſy is there? that we ſhould not run into. It is the Lord that keeps us, or elſe we ſhould have periſhed. Oh what cauſe hath every ſoul that hath been kept in the truth to bleſs God, that hath given them his ſpirit to lead them in the truth? It is not our parts, nor wiſdom, nor any thing in us that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth us from errour; he that beguiled <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency might eaſily beguile us, that have ſo much darkneſs in our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, impurity in our affections, and perverſneſs in our our wills. Our ſoules bleſs the Lord, and acknowledge that it is of his infinite grace and mercy to us that we have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. We have cauſe to ſay as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> did, <hi>Not unto us, but is to thy name be the praiſe.</hi> this ſhould be as a bond in our ſpirits to walk with God. The goodneſs of God ſhould have that effect on us, as it had on <hi>Jacob,</hi> when God appeared to him in <hi>Bethel;</hi> it is ſaid he lifted up his feet and went on his way. So it ſhould be with us, it ſhould make us lift up our feet and walk on in the waies of the Lord:</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104103:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
